So, welcome to the TRT and hormone
optimization YouTube channel and we have
a new guest today, Mike Belkin. Welcome,
Mike.
Uh thanks for having me here, Dr. Dee.
It's great to be here. Uh
huge huge fan of your your channel and
your Facebook page, so uh happy to be a
guest.
Yeah, thank you so much. So, maybe
introduce yourself. Uh
Um how did you become um provider for
TRT?
Sure, sure. Yeah, so my name is Mike
Belkin. I'm a nurse practitioner. I live
in Phoenix, Arizona.
Um you know, I started my started my
health care career and I age myself, but
it goes, you know, I've been doing in
this
in health care in some way or another
for about 30 years or so.
Uh but along the way, uh so I've been
you know, ER nurse, ICU nurse. I saw a
lot of um
a lot of people who waited too long to
take control of their health and had
some pretty dire consequences.
So, it really kind of kind of pushed me
into the field of um
you know, wellness wellness medicine.
What can we do to keep people healthy,
keep them out of those places, keep them
out of those situations, get them back
to doing the things they want to do.
>> [snorts]
>> And it just really kind of dovetailed
into the rest of the way I like to live
my life. I'm someone who's always been
into fitness and you know, working out
since I was a teenager and trying to
take good care of myself.
Um so, it's really it's a it's a nice
kind of medicine to to to practice. So,
now I'm enjoying most of my days helping
people stay healthy and stay out of
those bad, you know, those bad
situations.
But yeah, so I'm in I'm in Phoenix. I
have a telemedicine clinic here, so I
see patients in Arizona, Colorado,
Florida, Washington, Montana.
And you know, we really the the main
focus is fixing hormones and fixing
metabolic health so people can live a
better you know, a better life. Um
Yeah, that's kind of that's kind of the
long and short of it.
Awesome.
I understood you have a special interest
in helping older guys. They older is
relative.
Um yeah, to become healthier, more
independent when they grow really old.
Um so,
why that interest? Why is it
so important for men in general getting
older to be strong, active, and
independent?
Sure. I mean, we want to get the most
time we can out of what you know, what
we have on this planet, all right? So,
it's never it's never too late. I see a
lot of people think, "Ah, I should have
done this when I was younger." And they
just kind of let it fall, you know, to
the wayside.
And that's just it's just not true. I
mean, ideally, yeah, you've been doing
this stuff your whole life. You're
taking care of yourself. You're building
up that, you know, that you know, that
that currency to to bring into your
older years. But it's never never too
late to start. There's even some good
you know, some good research and some
good studies showing that elderly you
know, men and women 70s, 80s plus
they can get a pretty good result doing
some strength training, right? They go
from someone who can't get themselves up
out out of a chair by themselves and now
they can get up and go. Now they're less
likely to fall. They're less likely to
fall, less likely to do something like
break a hip. You stay out of the
hospital, you stay healthy. Now you're
able to spend your years um
you know,
doing the things you want to do instead
of being in a place like a nursing home.
So, I think it's a hugely hugely
important thing and I think it's a it's
a population that's kind of that kind of
can get passed by. People think they're
too old too old to start replacing their
hormones, to start you know, too old to
start their kind of you know, their
fitness
their fitness journey, but it's never
never too late. Start from where you
are.
What do you consider
older men
to get on TRT? What age?
Yeah, that's tricky. My
it's a sliding scale here. The older I
get, the you know, the
the
higher I push the age of what I consider
to be old, right? So, I'm 51 years old
now, you know, 20 years ago I would have
thought I'm a grandpa, but you know,
here here I am. 51 years old. I feel
great. Probably better than I did at 31.
Um no, but you know, what you know, what
do I consider what do I consider older?
Um
Yeah, I mean, I I I think
I think probably, you know, guys in
their in their 60s plus is when they
really start you know, start thinking
that it's
maybe other providers would consider a
contraindication or they're more
concerned about doing it, right? Guys in
their 30s, 40s, 50s, pretty much
anywhere they go, no one's going to balk
at it. People
they'll start you on TRT whether it's
your
you know, you know, probably not your
primary care, but you know, going to
another another clinic somewhere. But
some of the older you know, you start
getting up into those older ages, some
of the some of the clinics will balk at
things a little bit. So, maybe you know,
maybe over 60 I think would maybe be
that that cut point. I guess if you
check blood and testosterone in most men
60 and older, you find they have low
testosterone, right?
For sure, for sure. And really it really
starts to fall. So, you know, there's
some there's some data to show that you
start losing you know,
the numbers are even changing, too. So,
these numbers even seem to be getting
lower and lower. You know, sometimes
guys even in their 30s are starting to
fall off, but certainly by your 40s and
50s, you start losing a percentage of
your testosterone year over year. You
know, it could be one you know, one
percentage per year depending upon the
study you look at and that just falls
over time. Uh but even more importantly,
you know, free testosterone is falling
faster than total testosterone.
And that's something that gets missed a
lot, too. You know, back to the primary
care setting, guys will go in. They you
know, they finally talk their primary
care provider into checking their
testosterone. They only check a total
testosterone. Maybe it looks pretty
good. It's middle of the range. Hey man,
you're 5 or 600. You're great. You know,
you're like a 30-year-old. Don't worry
about it. But they didn't go beyond
that. They didn't check a sex hormone
binding globulin, so they can't
calculate a free testosterone. Um and
the free testosterone falls even
further, you know, even further over
over time. Uh the older you get, sex
hormone binding globulin kind of keeps
rationing up. Um that binds that's
literally what it sounds like it does.
It binds up the the free available
testosterone.
So, in the background, your numbers are
dropping faster than you than you think.
And it can it can it can drop pretty
significantly. Guys can get pretty
symptomatic from it. Yeah. And how come
those men wait so long to to seek help?
>> [laughter]
>> A lot of times people just chalk it up
to aging. They say and they'll they'll
even hear that from their provider. Hey
man, you're just getting older.
Right? What are you doing? You're trying
to chase. You're not going to be 25
forever. And that's fine, right? I mean,
it's not realistic to think you're going
to be 25 forever. But also, I think it's
important to make sure you don't wind up
65, 75, 85 and broken, right? That that
should be the bigger the bigger more
important goal.
Um but they yeah, people wait because
they just they just think it's part of
the way it should be. Hey, I'm not going
to you know, things aren't going to work
the way they used to be. Whatever it
might be, you know, their
you know, their aesthetics, the way they
look, their physical strength, their
their mental clarity even, their sexual
function. People just assume it that's
the way it has to be and it doesn't.
And is the treatment plan for HRT
different when men seek help on
35, 40 years than on 60 plus? Is the
the way you deal with it different?
The basics are really the same, right?
So, you know, symptom relief is king.
So, we're looking to relieve symptoms. I
do find with some older guys that they
find symptom relief without getting to
quite quite the higher you know, the
higher numbers.
You know, the average guy you know, free
testosterone seems to correlate a lot
better with symptom relief and total
testosterone. So, free testosterone you
know, 20 to 40 nanograms per deciliter
for most guys.
Um you know, a lot of older guys they're
on the lower end of that when they start
feeling good and feeling some relief.
Everyone's going to be different and you
have to kind of meet them where they are
and and see how they do you know,
symptomatically. But it seems like and
it could be that they've just been
living so low and in such a bad state
for so long that any kind of boost feels
better.
And there's always room to work, too, so
right? Maybe they might feel great. Man,
we got their free testosterone to 20
nanograms per deciliter. They're feeling
I'm feeling great. Maybe we can push it
a little bit further from there. But
yeah, that's the only that's the the
main real big difference that that I
see. Um I think the other thing would be
is you really have to be living
you know, living the life to match the
hormone level you're trying to
accomplish.
So, if you're you know, if you're an
older guy who's been taking great care
of yourself your whole life, we're
talking more about your you know, your
your biological age and your
chronological age.
You know, you might be you might be 70
years old and look like you're 50. You
might be fitter than the guy in the gym
who's you know, who's 40. That guy's
going to tolerate a higher level a lot
better than the guy who's been doing
nothing and is now 60 or 70 that thinks,
"Man, I need to do something. Let's plug
in some testosterone." Uh that guy might
be it might be running a little too hot
if we try to if we try to get his levels
too high too fast. You know, you can't
just um
you can't pour rocket fuel into your you
know, into your 74 or your 84
Toyota Tercel and and hope that it's
just going to run like a Ferrari. You
have to you have to build up the rest of
the chassis and get some better wheels
on there, get the whole the whole system
running fine before you can really get
those levels up a little bit higher.
Yeah, sure. As for those men 60 and
over,
if they contact you and they haven't
taken care of themselves very well,
maybe they are overweight or obese.
Do you Do you start them out on
lifestyle changes, diet, and exercise
first and afterwards TRT or do you start
everything at once?
That's a great that's a great question.
Um because the the two work better the
short answer is I do it concurrently,
right? So, I do it at the same time. Um
you know, in a perfect world, what I'm
what I'm hoping is not going to happen
is they're just going to take the
medicine and sit around and wait for it
to work
because they're going to end up
disappointed.
Right? I mean, there are studies that
show that just testosterone on its own
is going to do is going to have some
improvements. It's going to improve some
metabolic health. It's going to improve
some muscle retention and prevent
sarcopenia.
But when you stack that with other
lifestyle things, like now you're
exercising, doing some good resistance
training, eating a good diet, dialing
dialing in your sleep and recovery a
little bit more, that's when it really
it's additive and it just really can
really take off. So so I do it at the
same time. Um I like to say that you
know, testosterone makes effort feel
good, but you still have to get up off
the couch.
Right? So we plug this in, you get
yourself doing these things, even if you
don't feel like doing it. I'll tell
people, you know, give me give me the
minimum. You know, you hate going to the
gym, you've never liked it, it's not
what you want to do.
Doesn't even have to be at the gym. Give
me two days of, you know, bodyweight
exercises at home in your living room in
between commercials while you're
watching a show or you know, after work
for a couple nights a week. Do that, you
know, do that for 6 months while we're
fixing your hormones.
Uh and most of the time they just end up
wanting wanting to do more. Right? So
that's the catalyst and now now off we
go. But yeah, I don't I don't like the
idea of waiting, you know, waiting for
them to fix the lifestyle stuff cuz it
might be it might be hard. They might be
really struggling and dragging and
they're tired and they're feeling tired
after work and they have some brain fog
and they're just they're not feeling up
to it. So you know, the the two can go
together. The hormones are the catalyst,
but you still have to get up and do that
work. Mhm.
I speak a little bit as a layman now,
but um isn't it dangerous uh to start
resistance training at that age if they
have never worked out? Uh maybe their
bones are a bit more brittle uh
and then uh
Yeah, I'm I'm going to say I think it's
dangerous not to.
Right? So you have uh you know, we have
you know, 50 cent word sarcopenia,
right? So that's kind of age-related or
you know, wasting wasting of muscle.
Um it's going to happen, right? So if
you're And there's different there's
different data on this too. When does it
actually start? I think sort of it
depends upon, you know, what what you've
been doing for your whole life.
But sometime in your, you know, 40s or
so, maybe a little past there, you're
going to start losing a percentage of
muscle year over year. And it's
interesting, it kind of correlates even
with the you know, with with the hormone
drop, too, right? So you know, maybe
it's somewhere like a
you know, you know, 1% of your of your
muscle mass per year or so, maybe a
maybe a half a percent on the on in
those younger those early younger years,
then accelerating more as you get into
your, you know, 60s plus. Uh but if
you're losing that muscle year over
year, 1%, it's not not a good thing,
right? You're going to be weak, you're
going to be frail, you're going to have
a fall, you're not going to recover well
from you know, if you God forbid have a
hospitalization or something, you know,
something like that.
Um and there's even uh there's even a
threshold, you know, the sarcopenic uh
disability threshold. You know, you lose
about 20 to 30% of your total uh of your
total baseline muscle mass,
and that's about where people are
impaired, right? Now they can't walk
well, they can't can't get up off the
floor if they if they fall, they're not
going to be able to prevent themselves
from falling.
So if you do some math there, if you're
using, you know, if you're losing 1% per
year, you're looking at that 20 or 30,
you know, 20 or 30 years to get to that
point where now you can't do anything.
You're not going to be not going to be
able to function. You're going to you're
going to get hurt.
So
the other, you know, the flip side of
that is is the older you get, you have
to be a little more careful and
deliberate with the way you do train.
Right? So I don't want to take a
75-year-old guy and sign him up for a
you know, CrossFit gym class day one and
he's going in there doing box jumps and
ballistic movements and Olympic lifts
and that's probably not a great idea.
But you get him in there just moving
full, you know, full range of motion,
careful basically just practicing the
exercises to begin with. They're going
to get some real good um you know,
newbie gains just like the you know,
just like the 20-year-old who's the
first time in the gym. They're going to
they're going to get some they're going
to get some good muscle growth out of
it.
Um I think you know, their joints and
bones are actually going to feel better
for it. Now there's some blood flow
getting in there. We're getting things
moving and it was some reduced pain and
some and definitely some better
function. Mhm. So uh So yeah, definitely
definitely not unsafe and I I think it's
mandatory. I mean, I I I insist all of
my patients do it. They're probably sick
of hearing me say it, but uh when they
do it, they're they're happy for it.
Mhm. It improves health for sure.
>> [snorts]
>> Is it more difficult for guys over 60 to
build muscle and lose weight?
Without a doubt.
Without a doubt it is it is for sure. It
is for sure. But it's not impossible.
And again, if you're talking about, you
know, someone who's had no they haven't
had that kind of stimulus at all,
they're still going to be able to do it.
Again, perfect world, you know, it's
like investing. If you, you know,
if you took the advice and started
investing right out of college and you
you built up those retirement accounts,
you're going to be great. You're going
to hit 40, 50, it's just smooth sailing,
everything's great. Retirement is going
to be great financially. Same thing with
with uh you know, with
with your health. You know, the sooner
you start doing those things, the
better. But you have you have to start
from, you know, start from where you
are. So again, if you're in your, you
know, if you're in your 60s, you can
still build some strength, you can still
build some muscle. It's going to be it's
going to be a little bit more difficult.
It has to be a little more planned. Uh
you know, the 20-year-old could just go
into the gym and pretty much smash and
do whatever they want. They're going to
recover and be fine.
If you're you know, if you're 70, you
can't do that. It has to be a little
more planned, a little more regimented.
Um definitely have to pay a lot more
attention to your your recovery, things
like your sleep and your you know, your
your stress and just uh recovering from
the bout of exercise you did so you
could come back and do more.
Mhm. But you can definitely make some uh
make some progress.
Mhm.
Okay. Let's switch to maybe the
practical side of TRT.
Um for those guys older than 60, um
TRT, do they need a higher dose to start
with or lower dose or just the same like
a 40-year-old guys?
Yeah, so it is going to really it's
going to depend upon again, we're back
we're back to symptoms again, and we're
talking about guys who are likely to
have that higher sex hormone-binding
globulin. So they might need, you know,
they might need a higher dose or a
different dosing um
uh schedule to overcome that high sex
hormone-binding globulin. That's really
kind of the kind of kind of the bigger
factor there.
Right? And everyone's different,
everyone has a different sensitivity,
there's some genetic component there,
too. So that really that really depends.
But otherwise, that's the
there's not a it's not a whole lot
different. It's not a whole lot
different. I don't I don't do it a whole
lot different with my with my older guys
than with my younger guys.
Mhm.
Do you um is your preferred um way of
administration injections?
I think injections and uh compounded
topical cream, right? You know, so 20%
topical cream. I know most everyone
listening to your channel's heard this a
thousand times, too, right? But just in
case someone's first time, I'm not
talking about AndroGel or that weak
sauce
uh stuff you see, the compounded 20%
cream applied transscrotally works I
think just as good if not better for you
know, for some people. Um I think it
you know, the more and more I I used to
be just really
way more pro-injection and not so much
for cream. But I I see so many guys
doing good good with cream and they have
a great outcome that I'm I'm a fan. I'm
a fan. I think it really works well.
Um I think it really comes down to
compliance and lifestyle and what you're
going to do.
If you're, you know, if you're someone
who's going to apply the cream twice per
day and actually stick to it and and uh
you know,
and do it consistently, it's going to
work it's going to work good. If you're
someone who knows you're not going to do
that, you know, it's not going to work
it's not going to work as good. Um
creams you have some sometimes have some
issues with, you know, absorption.
Um or if you have some worry about
transference,
so a lot of times with older guys, some
of those issues just aren't an issue
anymore, right? The kids are gone out of
the house, they're not worried about
transference in that way. Um they have a
pretty good schedule because they're
either, you know, they're either retired
or they have a work schedule that lets
them be pretty flexible. So applying a
cream twice per day isn't isn't a big
deal. They're not rushing out of the
house to have their, you know, 14-hour
work day like that, you know, 30- or
40-year-old guy might be doing. So for
you know, for a lot of guys um for that
reason, the cream could work could work
pretty good. Mhm.
I also see sometimes the cream work
better for guys who are not quite as
healthy.
Uh there's there's something there's
something to the short half-life and the
fact that it kind of uh you know, we get
this this these kind of two waves,
right? Two two twice-daily
administration.
With the injection, you're kind of
getting these levels and we're kind of
we're kind of keeping these steady
levels as it goes throughout the without
the week. And there's some small, you
know, some small peaks and troughs, but
not not quite the same.
So for some of these kind of less
metabolically or over you know, overall
less healthy guys, the cream could
actually work a little bit better. Um as
in they just they just feel they just
feel a little bit better. Um
so it it but it's it's it's it's
individual. But either either one works
great.
Mhm.
Do you find that um men over 60 are more
often hypothyroid as well? Do you check
and treat both?
I do. I see a lot of I see a lot of
hypothyroidism. A lot of it. Um I do I I
screen all of my patients for that, too,
right? I like to get some labs. Um You
know, at least a thyroid-stimulating
hormone and a free T3. You know, free T3
can kind of equate it the way you do
with free testosterone. I mean, there's
there's there's some differences with
way the you know, the
uh with you know, with TSH and the
feedback loop, um you're not going to
completely shut down the way you do with
testosterone. So in a way you could kind
of top things off a little bit with
thyroid.
But I do see a lot of guys um
you know, sometimes they're you know,
their TSH, if you look at a lab range on
a TSH, you'll see a lot you know, some
labs will have it you know, 0.25 to five
or you know, some something like that,
some absurd range.
And they'll go to their PCP, maybe they
check it every year, maybe every couple
years, and they just say, "Hey, it's in
that same range, it's normal." No one
ever checks another range, you know,
another value, no free T3, no thyroid
antibodies. Um that TSH is slowly
creeping up. The guy's slowly getting
more tired and having more brain fog and
maybe, you know, feeling chilly. He's a
guy wearing a sweater in the office now,
that kind of thing. And no one ever
thought to check it. And then you know,
they come to someone like me and or one
of the one of our providers and and uh
you know, we check their thyroid and
it's crazy they have a TSH that's four
and they have a free T3 that's two.
Right? So you know, optimal TSH I'd
rather see people with a you know, a TSH
closer to one and a free T3 maybe you
know, three and a half to five. Now
people are feeling good, right? They
need less stimulants. They're you know,
they might have gone from being the guy
in the morning who wakes up and just
can't wait to have that cup of coffee
and now they just they just don't even
have that morning cup or maybe it's
11:00. Like holy cow man, I didn't even
have any coffee yet. I didn't even know
I needed it. And now you savor it when
you really need it. It's even more
effective. You use it to fuel your
workout or what you know, whatever it
might be.
So thyroid's a huge part of it. I think
all all the hormones all all come
together. I mean, you know, testosterone
is kind of the star of the show and the
one everyone wants to talk about but uh
replacing thyroid along with it can
really be a nice can really be a nice
thing. It helps it helps a lot of folks.
Mhm.
And do you put them on both hormones,
testosterone and thyroid hormone at the
same time or do you wait for the results
uh from the first one?
Yeah, and that's that's where it gets a
little tricky, right? So if you're
changing you know, if you're changing
too many if you have too many moving
parts at one time, you don't know what
did what. What made you feel better or
even worse what you know, what made you
feel worse, right? If then
hey, I'm taking these medications
something's going on. I don't feel
right.
Uh so you know, I do I I do like to do
them kind of kind of one at a time. Um
sometimes if things are really you know,
everything just out of whack and I have
someone who's you know, really eager to
get started. I I explain this whole
process to them that hey, you know, it
might be hard to tell which is which.
And sometimes they're on board for just
doing both. So occasionally I'll do
both.
Usually I'll fix um
uh usually I'll fix testosterone first
but it really depends upon the patient.
Mhm.
All right. Um about libido, do those
guys more than over 60 um
complain more often than younger guys? I
guess yes.
You know, everyone seems to complain
about their uh about their libido these
days. Even the younger guys. Even the
younger guys. But no, for for sure for
sure the older guys. And it definitely
gives them a boost in their libido with
without a doubt. Um it's one of the
reasons that I kind of emphasize. I
think it's important to treat um
um you know, treat couples or make sure
everyone else in the relationship is on
is on board cuz you fix you know, you
fix one libido without fixing the other
and you can have a problem.
So it definitely uh but no, it's it's a
common complaint. It's a common
complaint with older guys for sure. Mhm.
And are there any add-ons uh for libido
you try out if testosterone doesn't do
the job?
You know,
even more so with the older guys, I like
to look at some of the other you know,
the other um
kind of upstream hormones, things like
DHEA or pregnenolone.
Um sometimes you can tweak you know, you
can tweak those a bit and really can
really get things you know, really get
things going. Um a lot of times it's
it's a matter of just fixing overall
health too, right? If someone's not
metabolically healthy, your body's not
looking to you know, to reproduce. It's
just not biologically in the you know,
in the in the works there. So you fix
some you know, you fix some health to
get someone leaner and more muscular and
exercising and fixing their
cardiovascular health. You know,
everything anything that's good for the
heart is also good for the you know,
good for the penis. So you you fix those
things and now boom boom it all it all
starts kind of coming kind of coming
together.
Mhm. Those are those are the kind of the
top line you know, the kind of the top
line things for for libido. Uh you know,
some of the some of the other things you
consider too. I mean there's some
peptides, you know, you have things like
PT-141 and those kinds of those kinds of
things. Those can sometimes help a bit.
Um most of the time we don't even have
to get there though. We stick with these
top tier things, fixing testosterone,
fixing thyroid, maybe DHEA,
pregnenolone, really work on health and
fitness and you know, leaning out and
building some muscle and it really all
seems to come together.
Mhm.
What about using tadalafil?
Oh yeah. No, it's a big it it it's a big
one. It's a big one and and I'm a fan.
I'm a fan. I think it has some good uh
some good longevity benefits too, right?
I mean you're improving endothelial
health.
I reduces blood pressure just a little
bit.
Um it can be it it it's a great
medication. So I'm I'm a fan of a low
dose you know, low dose 5 mg per day
for you know, not only older guys. I
think for
for I mean men for many folks, it just
has some has some great benefits there.
Yeah, gives a little the little extra
little extra boost and little extra
confidence and then you also you know,
you're also taking a medication that you
know is doing some other good things for
your health. So it's an easy sell. I I
prescribe a lot of it. Mhm.
Any other supplements or add-ons that
you always recommend to
men getting on TRT?
Yeah, you know,
I see I just see a lot of people seem to
be deficient in vitamin D, right? So I
like to you know, vitamin D with some K2
it's going to help just about everyone.
It's going to help some immune function.
You know, it has a lot of good hormonal
effects it just across the board for
general health. I think everyone we
should be you know, we should be there.
Um same thing with zinc. I think it's a
commonly missed one. It really helps
with some immunity. Especially you know,
as you're getting older too, you're more
common to get you know, even just more
common colds and that kind of thing. So
if you're staying on top of that, I
think it can be a real a real helpful
thing.
Um I like some magnesium at bedtime. Um
you know, I'm I'm a fan of magnesium
glycinate. It's easy you know, easy on
the gut, takes the edge off. Um
uh you know, takes the edge off the
nerves and helps you know, helps you
sleep just a little bit better. Uh most
people seem even you know, just a little
bit deficient especially folks who are
exercising hard and sweating you know,
and sweating a lot. So I'm I'm I'm a fan
of uh magnesium too.
Mhm.
What else supplement wise?
Those are kind of some of my big ones. I
mean I think something like creatine is
an easy uh you know, an easy sell too.
An easy add-on for for most people. It
has some good you know, has some good
cognitive effects too. Can help with
some brain health. So I like that I like
that a lot for you know, for aging folks
also. Mhm.
Dr. Keith Nichols you know him from the
channel as well. Sure. Yeah, yeah. Yeah,
he has helped me getting on TRT in 2017
and yeah, I learned from him that older
men but I think he already calls them
older if they are 45
plus.
He said older men have to get all the
hormones replaced. So testosterone,
thyroid, DHEA, pregnenolone,
melatonin. So the whole bunch.
Everyone gets the whole bunch.
That was his opinion at least. Yeah, I
know mel I I did leave out melatonin
there. I'm also a big fan of melatonin.
Mhm. I think for less important for
younger people but it just you know,
it's been known for for a long time your
melatonin just falls off. It's the you
know, why do you know, why do old people
you know, why do they they're they're
they're sleeping four or five hours?
They just get up. They pop out of bed
and there they go and I go oh man but
you know, and they need that rest and
recovery still.
It's not that they don't not that they
don't need it. It's just they're you
know, they're they're missing out here.
So I think I think uh some melatonin can
be a real a real nice thing. I like to
start like you know, three to five
milligrams and kind of titrate up. Um
you know, younger people I don't like to
go too high. Maybe keep it you know,
five five-ish milligrams or so unless
you're going for a real you know, real
big specific effect. But for older
people like you know, older guys you
know, the old old guys over you know,
over 50 I guess we can say. Um you can
you can you can crank up that dose quite
a bit, right? I have a lot of guys
taking 20 mg a night and they feel they
feel great. They get a more restful
sleep. Um it's just you're doing some
good some good things.
You [snorts] know, high dose melatonin
even think it might have some
anti-cancer effect too, right? So you
get some nice some nice benefits there.
Mhm. Yeah. Yeah. How much how much do
you take? Yeah, I've been taking 50 mg
since
>> Okay. years now. Yeah, I I take it
rather
I was never groggy on whatever dose. So
been taking that forever. Yeah. Yeah,
did you gradually you ramped it up
gradually though? Yeah, gradually but
rather rapidly every month a bit uh 5 mg
more.
I I didn't feel groggy ever and together
with um magnesium in the evening and
always had a good time sleeping. So
Yeah, it's a nice it's a nice combo for
sleep for sure.
Yeah, so mag so magnesium, some
melatonin. Um you know, if guys want a
little extra an extra add-on for sleep
too, I I like some occasional glycine in
there too. You know, like three to five
grams of glycine. It's a powdered you
know, powdered stuff has a little bit of
sweet taste to it. Helps give you a
little bit of a GABA boost. So I like I
like that occasionally too.
But yeah, melatonin is a is a good one.
I'm I'm a fan.
>> [sighs]
>> Um let me get back to the
overweight or obese guys. Do you use any
of the peptides there for them
semaglutide and so on?
Oh yeah. No, those drugs drugs those
drugs are amazing. You know,
semaglutide, tirzepatide, fantastic
stuff. I mean I think if we're talking
about
you know, longevity drugs, I think
testosterone's really one of our top you
know, checking a lot of boxes there. But
then you know, maybe maybe even equally
dependent upon the person we're talking
about and what they need you know, what
they need fixed. Those modern weight
loss medications are kind of top tier
longevity drugs. I mean you you you fix
you fix obesity and lose some adiposity,
you you just fix so many things. Yeah.
Uh I mean metabolic markers start coming
back in the in the play here. Um you
know, adiposity or fat tissue is
inflammatory so you're knocking out
inflammation so people are in less pain.
They're able to move better. Now they're
able to do that exercise and it just
kind of really rolls you know, rolls
along with it.
So you're now you're um you know, now
you're improving you know, improving
insulin sensitivity, reversing
pre-diabetes or even diabetes, losing
body fat, you're moving more, you're
reducing incidence of fatty liver. There
just so many so many great benefits
there. I think they're I think they're
fantastic meds and the combination um
of testosterone and and modern weight
loss meds like those are are are great
are great. Um I would even add I think
it's you know you start getting it gets
even more more important to have an
emphasis on on things that are going to
keep muscle which includes testosterone
and and resistance training when you're
taking those medications
because if you're you know if you're um
uh if you're losing weight you're going
to be in a caloric deficit. These
medications make you eat less and crave
less. So the bottom line is you're
eating less food and that's how you're
that's how you're losing your body fat
and losing the weight. So right? So
you're going to lose tissue. It's a
matter of what kind of tissue are you
going to lose, right? So if you're doing
the things to keep your muscle you're
going to lose mostly fat. If you're not
you might lose half you know half of
that body weight you're losing is
muscle. Then you end up with uh you know
it's not the look most people are going
for to lose half their muscle, right?
The scale weight looks great but they
look at themselves in the mirror and go
you know what happened here. Yeah. So
yeah so I'm so I'm a big fan. All all of
my patients I have on those on those
modern weight loss medications I I
insist they eat you know they hit their
protein goal. I insist they do some sort
of resistance training. Um slow
reasonable diet you know the the um
um
the you know the good the the good
basics of of quality diet dieting still
apply when you're using these
medications. It's not some magic thing.
You still need to lose at a slow
consistent pace. I think paired together
that's some that's some magic stuff.
Mhm.
Do you find there are um
contraindications
in some patients for TRT if they are
getting older? Maybe um I don't know a
PSA that is too high or uh
heart uh and cardiovascular issues.
Yeah I can start I can start getting a
little bit a little bit tricky there.
You know some of the biggest ones starts
to be some of the um you know some some
of the PSA and some of the some of the
prostate you know some of the prostate
concerns. Most of the PSA concerns end
up being a transient thing. It ends up
being some you know some prostatitis or
something like that and it kind of
transient and it goes away. Maybe it
means a trip to urology to kind of get
some things checked out. Um you
definitely I mean
the bottom line is you don't want to
treat a guy with testosterone as active
prostate cancer. That's just a bad you
know a bad set of facts. But outside of
that you're really you know you're
really okay. It's not going to give you
prostate cancer. It's not going to give
you prostate problems. Um you just you
just kind of monitor it and deal deal
with that as it as it comes.
Um as far as the cardiovascular risk go
it's interesting because you know even
some some very recent studies kind of
backed away and kind of pulled back on
the old you know testosterone as a
cardiovascular risk. It just kind of
showed that it's just not it's just
really not a thing. It's not a it's not
a it's not a concern like you know what
like like we once thought.
So not a not not a problem there. Um
you know there is some concern that
maybe some older guys are a little bit a
little bit more prone to some you know
some arrhythmias and that that kind of
that kind of thing. And I can same kind
of same kind of deal there when you're
replacing thyroid with older guys. You
know you want to have them keep an eye
out. It's something I warn people about.
Hey let me know if you notice this is an
irregular heart rate or a fast heart
rate.
Pretty pretty uncommon thing. I think a
lot of those you know a lot of those
findings were that's just going to
happen to some older people. They just
happen to be on these medications. So
probably not as big a big a concern as
we as we think there. Mhm.
And how is the relationship between you
the provider for their HRT TRT and the
general practitioner? Because
I guess sometimes the general
practitioner is a bit more worried than
you about their patients
heart disease or whatever.
I I I tell you this because you know as
a dermatologist
I'm prescribing isotretinoin. I'm
prescribing antimycotic medication and
all things like that. And very [snorts]
often almost weekly I hear from patients
oh my general practitioner said this was
bad for my liver. This was bad for my
kidneys. I I I don't uh dare to take
that medication. So the general
practitioner sometimes uh frightens
my patient from the medication he should
take. So what's your take on that?
It happens. You know it happens less
less often than
than it used to. I feel like less and
and I I think part of it could be just
because people are going to see their
their general practitioner less and less
and they're actually spending less time
with them. So the fact the fact that
they have these ultra short visits where
they're in there talking to their you
know their doctor for 5 minutes they
just don't have time to cover all this.
Sometimes they don't even you know maybe
it doesn't even come up at all. Um so I
think I think that in in a way has been
a been a blessing. So now that you know
the PCP just doesn't even have to get
involved with it at all. But I do see it
a lot. I've seen I've seen um guys who
are on it and stopped and then they come
back to me because they want to you know
they maybe they want to revisit it and
restart because they remember how good
they felt. They'll have a story like
that like hey you know my doctor told me
I really dodged the bullet here by by
you know by talking about it and getting
him off of there cuz I was going to he
was he was going to give me a heart
attack and prostate cancer and I was
going to get a blood clot and so on you
know and so on and so on. And those
things are just you know they're they're
they're old news. And I don't blame the
primary care doctors 100% right? They're
not they're not
it's not their niche. They're not in
there paying close attention to the
latest the latest on all of it. But also
they're they are they are passing along
some bad you know some bad information.
So
uh I I haven't had any any situations
where um
um where I've had to have a a talk with
their primary care or you know any kind
of butting heads and like that that kind
of thing. But I've I've had some people
leave their primary care provider over
it. Right? They'll talk to me and say
hey you know I'm just I just went and
found someone else. We're not on the
same page with this. And I think that's
I think that's fine too.
Yeah. Yeah
here in Belgium
we we even have that very often with the
pharmacies.
So you prescribe something the patients
go to the pharmacy and the pharmacist
says oh that's a very heavy medication
for it's very bad for your liver. Do you
really have to take that? And then the
patient is frightened and they don't buy
the the medication. They come back to me
and they say no I didn't take it. I was
afraid and the pharmacy warned me about
this and this side effect. Uh so and
then they ask me so what should I do
now? I say uh ask the pharmacy what you
should do. Yeah.
We No I tell you it it puts us in a bad
spot, right? Because now now the patient
is confused. Like hey what do what do I
do here? Do I trust this guy? You know I
thought I trusted this guy. Seemed like
he knew what he was talking about. Now
here's this other medical professional
giving me a whole different whole
different look at it. Same thing happens
here with the pharmacies.
Right? Um in the in the you know in the
US a lot of us will use you know we use
compounding pharmacies instead. And a
lot of it is because we're on the same
you know we're on the same page about
treatment. Right? So these pharmacists
are more trained in that. They're more
knowledgeable about it. We can call and
get you know get good actually get good
advice from them instead of instead of
this you know this other these other
scare tactics that the that the patients
hear. So I try to avoid the you know the
those kind of pharmacies for these these
things if I can. Um I've even ran into
that myself when I was trying to fill my
own armor thyroid at at a pharmacy here.
The pharmacist asked me uh
what did she say? She said oh have you
had blood work for this? Do you really
need this kind of thing?
And it it was amazing. I was like are
you the you're not the just fill the
prescription. Right? What what are we
talking about here? So it was
interesting to see what what patients
might go through. Yeah. Yeah it's common
practice here. Even 25 years ago when I
was a still an intern in dermatology I I
remember my professor calling the
pharmacy and he was very angry because
they also frightened his patient and he
said the only thing you have to do is
sell those pills to the patient and just
shut up. And
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah. Nice. Still going on.
>> Yeah. 25 years later still going on
every week. Yeah.
Yeah no it's sad that it has to turn
into that into that sometimes. Everyone
wants to hold their you know stand their
ground on their on their beliefs there.
Yeah it's it's crazy. It's crazy.
Yeah. Maybe back to the HRT. I had
another question about
growth hormone and maybe growth hormone
secretagogues or releasing peptides.
Because I guess when you get even older
than 60 old growth hormone secretion is
gone. Do those secretagogues still work?
Do you recommend them? Um
It it it gets interesting right? Because
we're in we're in an interesting um
interesting spot with growth hormone.
Because if you're talking about just you
know replacing growth hormone
uh just straight up you know
injecting it or straight in there
the the legalities of it and
availability it's just really it just
really not a not a thing in most uh you
know definitely not in the US. You have
to have real special indications for it.
It's even you know it's even a felony to
prescribe if you do it wrong and there's
all all these things. So very very very
narrow indication there.
And I think the secretagogues can be
great but a lot of it's going to depend
upon the health of your system. Right?
Because we're asking the pituitary to
now um
uh
now now secrete more growth hormone on
its own. And is it healthy and up to
that task?
Right? So you get you get to a point
where what are you actually going to get
out of it? Um
uh and I think at best too you know some
some of the levels that they that they
show with these like maybe you get like
a 30 or 40% boost from that. Right? So
maybe if you had a healthy you know a
healthy pituitary maybe you're getting
the equivalent of like you know people
who understand growth hormone you know
if you're talking about it in units
maybe you're getting like the equivalent
of a unit or two of of what you'd get
from exogenous growth hormone out of a
secretagogue. Which could be pretty
good. Right? Now you're getting better
sleep. You're getting better recovery.
But it's hard to know what what you're
going to get until you until you try. So
I I think it's an okay okay thing to
try, right? I think older guys, you
know, the expectation should be, you
know, that this might work, it might
not. You can give it a try. Maybe you
check an IGF-1 level, which is a you
know, it's an okay okay test and an okay
measure. I don't put a lot of a lot of
weight on it. A lot of things can affect
that, you know, that that number. So I
like to see how people feel. I think you
know, some of these are creative gods
just
improve people's sleep. I think that's a
great metric to go by, right? If you're
taking something like you know, a lot of
these things in the US just aren't
available anymore. But if you're taking
something like Tesamorelin or Sermorelin
and you're you're using it you know,
five six nights a week and you're
getting five six nights a week of way
better sleep. I think that's a win right
there. I don't care what it's doing to
your growth hormone or what it's
actually doing to your IGF levels long
term. You're going to get some you're
going to get some benefit from that
alone. So I so I do like it for that.
And I think that's a I think that's a
fine way to a fine way to use those
things.
Mhm. Fine.
All right, Mike. I think we've covered a
lot. Are there any other differences
for men getting on HRT in general
between 35, 40 and a 60 plus? Any other
differences?
I think one of the biggest differences
is you know, time is of the essence
here, right? I mean, you have
you only have so much you know, some
only have so much time on this planet.
So you need to make the most of it. So
if it's you know, if you're getting up
there in your age and you're going to do
it, do it
do it now. Do it now, right? It's going
to it's going to keep you healthy. It's
going to keep you keep you around doing
the things you want to you know, you
want to do longer.
As far as the specifics of doing it, I
think it's a matter of just just getting
after it and doing it. Go see go see a
competent provider. You know, don't
waste your time going to your PCP and
ask them about it. Get in to see a
specialist on this thing. Get some blood
work done.
And you can get you get you feeling get
you feeling better.
Awesome.
Any last advice for men watching older
than 60?
Yeah, I think you know,
not to not to make it sound morbid, but
you know, sometimes people will ask me,
you know, hey, what do you what are you
training for? You know, what are you
doing? You know, when you're younger,
there might be some sort of an outward
goal like you know, I just want to I
want to get in better shape for the
beach or I want to be strong. I want to
compete in this, you know, with
powerlifting whatever it might be or
some sort of a sport.
As you get older, you know, some of
these interests fall off. You're not as
interested. I mean, everyone still wants
to look good. Everyone still wants to be
strong. Maybe you still want to you
know, do some sport, but it's not not as
high a priority.
So I think you know, as that starts to
fade, it's good to focus on the bigger
priority of
you know, how about the sport of life,
right? This is going to keep you around
longer and healthier and doing the
things you want to do.
And eventually, I mean, hopefully not. I
hope that we're both you know, some of
the lucky ones it doesn't happen to, but
at some point you're going to have some
sort of an event. Right? I mean, whether
that be a you know, a cardiac event, a
cerebrovascular event, or a trauma, an
illness, a surgery, you're going to need
to bounce back from that thing.
So come into that event strong. People
who come into those things strong leave
strong. People who come into those
things weak sometimes don't leave at
all. Right? So if you need a big if you
need a motivation to to do this stuff,
there you know, there it is. There it
is. You know, you you don't want to wake
up in your in the in the ICU bed
realizing that you should have been
building up your you know, building up
your muscle and having that metabolic
currency to get you through this you
know, get you through this thing. Yeah.
I think I think that's a hugely a hugely
important thing. And I think a lot of
people listening to this channel too are
probably thinking, well, you know,
that's not me anyway. You know, I'm
doing all these things, right? You have
some pretty pretty high level folks
listening to this that are really into
this stuff. But most of them also have
family members who aren't or friends who
aren't. And if they're looking for a
motivation, it's a good way to kind of
you know, kind of try to sell this
thing. Be a good ambassador of health
and fitness and you know, pass that
along to a loved one so you can spend
you know, spend more time with them.
Yeah. That's a big that's a big thing. I
saw
definitely I saw a ton of that working
in the hospitals. It was a shame. People
would come in. You could tell who was
going to who this is going to go well
for and who it wasn't. Mhm. You'd have
people you know, some some bad thing
happens. No one could have seen it
coming. You know, the guy's in great
shape.
You know, bounces back great. He's
discharged home directly from the ICU
and you know, not
you know,
things aren't perfect, but he's going to
be okay, right? It's going to be all
right. Someone comes in weak, it's a
prolonged hospital stay. They're losing
twice as much muscle. They're going to
rehab. Maybe they're going to
they're going to a nursing home and
that's it. You know, it's it's it's
going to be some life changing stuff.
So I think it's a I think it's an
important point to keep in mind. Sure.
And as a medical provider, we also need
to lead by example, right? I I think
it's usually important, right? Right? I
mean, yeah, if you come in there, you
know, you want to have
your your your your practice is primary
dermatology, right? Right.
Yeah, so people want to come in. They
want to see a guy who's you know, who's
who looks who looks good. He's healthy
overall. He has good skin, right? You go
see a dermatologist with bad skin.
You're wondering, hey, does this guy
know what he's talking about? What are
we doing here?
No, but yeah, you want to be yeah, you
want to you want to look the you want to
look the look the part and walk you
know, walk the walk. And
yeah, it's it definitely helps helps
make the sale. It helps get more people
where they need to be.
Mhm.
All right, Mike. Thank you so much for
sharing your knowledge and experience.
If people want to reach out to you, how
do they do that?
Sure. So you can find me everywhere
men's health span, right? So men's
health span.com.
You can reach me by email
mike@menshealthspan.com.
All the social medias, I think I have uh
Facebook,
Instagram, TikTok, YouTube, all men's
health span. So I have some videos and
stuff up there too. But yeah, someone
someone wants to reach out, shoot me a
message. I'm happy to chat.
Okay. Thank you so much again.
Yeah, thanks for having me. This has
been fun. It was a pleasure.